<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Exceeding joyfull newes from the Earl of Bedford, Lord Generall of the Horse, that is now set forth for the defence of the Protestant religion. Declaring the happy and fortunate successe of the Ptotestant [sic] army at Siege-moore in Sommersetshire, upon the 19. day of this instant month of August, who having received a challange from the Lord Paulet, Sir Ralph Hopton, and Sir John Stowell, daring them to meet them at the said moor at the time and place appointed. Which said gentlemen upon the 19. day assembled at Siege-moor with great number of men, where Sir Francis Popham, Mr. Pine, and Mr. Stroud met them wich [sic] 6000. horse and foot, and after some parley concerning the King and Parliament, they fell to blowes, but after some 6, hours fight Sir Francis obtained the victory. The said Lord Paulet and his accomplices stood for the commission of array, and Sir Francis and the rest of the gentlemen for the ordinance of Parliament.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84253</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3757</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E113_17</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17793</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860271</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860271</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112389</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84253)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112389)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 20:E113[17])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Exceeding joyfull newes from the Earl of Bedford, Lord Generall of the Horse, that is now set forth for the defence of the Protestant religion. Declaring the happy and fortunate successe of the Ptotestant [sic] army at Siege-moore in Sommersetshire, upon the 19. day of this instant month of August, who having received a challange from the Lord Paulet, Sir Ralph Hopton, and Sir John Stowell, daring them to meet them at the said moor at the time and place appointed. Which said gentlemen upon the 19. day assembled at Siege-moor with great number of men, where Sir Francis Popham, Mr. Pine, and Mr. Stroud met them wich [sic] 6000. horse and foot, and after some parley concerning the King and Parliament, they fell to blowes, but after some 6, hours fight Sir Francis obtained the victory. The said Lord Paulet and his accomplices stood for the commission of array, and Sir Francis and the rest of the gentlemen for the ordinance of Parliament.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, for Thomas Berriman; dwelling in Great St. Bartholomews,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>August 23. 1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bedford, William Russell, --  Duke of, 1613-1700 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Somerset (England) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Campaigns --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:112389:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Exceeding Joyfull NEWES FROM The Earl of <hi>Bedford,</hi> Lord Generall of the Horſe, that is now ſet forth for the Defence of the Proteſtant RELIGION.</p>
            <p>Declaring the happy and fortunate Succeſſe of the Proteſtant Army at Siege-Moore in Sommerſet-ſhire, upon the 19. day of this inſtant month of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> who having received a <hi>Challenge</hi> from the <hi>Lord Paulet,</hi> Sir <hi>Ralph Hopton,</hi> and Sir John Stowell, daring them to meet them at the ſaid Moor at the time and place appointed.</p>
            <p>Which ſaid Gentlemen upon the 19. day aſſembled at Siege-Moor with a great number of men, where Sir <hi>Francis Popham,</hi> Mr. <hi>Pine,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Str<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd</hi> met them with 6000. Horſe and Foot and after ſome parley concerning the King and parliament, they fell to blowes, but after ſome 6, hours fight. Sir <hi>Francis</hi> obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Victory.</p>
            <p>The ſaid Lord <hi>Paulet</hi> and his Accomplices ſtood for the <hi>Commiſſion of Array,</hi> and Sir <hi>Francis</hi> and the reſt of the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men for the <hi>Ordinance of Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> Printed, for <hi>Thomas Berriman;</hi> dwelling in Great St. <hi>Bartholomews.</hi> Anguſt 23. 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="newsbook">
            <pb facs="tcp:112389:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:112389:2"/>
            <head>Exceeding Joyfull NEVVS FROM FROM Sommerſet-ſhire.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>N the 16. day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> there was a meeting of divers Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen at Sir <hi>Iohn Stowell</hi> his houſe at <hi>Ham,</hi> where after much diſcourſe amongſt them ſelves, they contrived away how they might put the <hi>Commiſſion of Array</hi> in execution, and ſuppreſſe all thoſe that ſhould op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them therin, Sir <hi>Ralph Hopton</hi> replyed, that it were an caſie thing to be done.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, conſidering my Lord <hi>Paul<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ts</hi> powerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the Eaſt part of the ſhire, and what mean Forces there abouts can ariſe to hinder his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings therin, the rather for his part in regard
<pb facs="tcp:112389:3"/>of Maſter <hi>Digbies</hi> aſſiſtance of Horſe and Foot.</item>
               <item>II. For his own part he ſaid he hath gotten the good will of the County therabouts his quarter, notwithſtanding Mr. <hi>Alexander Popham,</hi> or Sir <hi>Iohn Horner,</hi> do they what they can.</item>
               <item>III. For <hi>Iihn Stowel</hi> it was ſaid his oppoſers were many, namely, Sir <hi>Francis Popham,</hi> Mr. <hi>Pine</hi> M. <hi>Coles,</hi> M. <hi>Nevvton,</hi> and divers others; yet they thought his part of the County were as eaſie to be brought under ſubjection, as any of them, all the rather, becauſe he hath great Lordſhips and Mannors about the Weſt part of the ſhire, and that his Tenants, moſt of them holdeth their Lands by Rack-rent; ſo that if they would not obey his command, he might out with them.</item>
               <item>IV. And laſtly, for Sir <hi>Francis Dorington,</hi> Sir <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinando Gorge,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Smith,</hi> they ſaid that they thought the Inhabitants of the City of <hi>Briſtoll,</hi> and <hi>Bath</hi> wovld help and aſſiſt them, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Mr. <hi>Hollis</hi> or Mr. <hi>Stroud;</hi> after which agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they concluded and prefixed a day, place, and hour, of meeting, which was the following, being ihe 18. of <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:112389:3"/>
            <p> And that every one of theſe Gentlemen <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore-mentioned, ſhould make what expedition they could in Raiſing each feverall mans quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and to force their Neighbors and Tenants <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o be well armed with powder and ſhot, and the Pikes to be in the Arrear of the Muſquetiers, and the Horſe to be in Arrear of all the Pikes, which was about the number of five thouſand ſouldiers, all o meet at a place called Siege-more, upon the Eleventh of Auguſt, about o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of the clock, at the Eaſt part of ſaid Moore, neere adjoyning to <hi>Donnington</hi> and <hi>Sommerton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Francis Popham</hi> and his Son Mr. <hi>Pine,</hi> Mr <hi>Stroud,</hi> and the reſt having had notice ſent them by theſe Cavaleers, that at ſuch a day, place, and houre, they would put the Commiſſion of Array in execution, in defiance of them all, that if any offered to oppoſe them in the execution thereof, let them be aſſured ehey ſhall ſuffer for their at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, though they hazzard their Lives and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes therein.</p>
            <p>The ſaid Sir <hi>Francis</hi> with the reſt of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y in the County, fearing no threatnings, cauſed the drums to beat up, charging the Trained Bands to be in readineſſe, and every Captain of the train Bands to lead his Company to the ſaid Moore at the day appointed, and about 6000 met at the place and hour, the Cavaleers themſelves durſt not venture neer their ſoldiers, for feare of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherie by their own Companies.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:112389:4"/>
            <p> For there was not a word of Command obeyed by the Cavaleers, upon which they all rid their wayes, and took their commanding ſervants and Sir <hi>Iohn Stowell</hi> dangerouſly ſhot in the breech, yet he got away before any could over take him, and the Country being thus met together on both ſides, the one part to put the <hi>Commiſsion of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ray</hi> in execution the other the <hi>Militia,</hi> conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all ingenerall to put the <hi>Militia</hi> in execution where they exerciſed for three hours ſpace, only three Captains in the Lord <hi>Paulets</hi> Regiment, and two Captains under M. <hi>Smith</hi> his Regiment, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to put their ſouldiers in ranck or file, or to exerciſe them.</p>
            <p>Whereupon they were apprehended and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to priſon, till Order from the Parliament.</p>
            <p>The Country ſince the laſt four Troope of Horſe, ſent by the Earl of <hi>Bedford,</hi> who is Lord Lieutenant of the ſhire, hath kept the Countrey in peace and quietneſſe, for they are quartered within a mile of each Gentlemans habitation or manſion houſe.</p>
            <p>The City of Wells hath been much rifled and racked, and the Cavaleers have poled and pinched the poor of the City, and hath made ſuch an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacle of the town, that it is not 10000. l. will make ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>The Town Goal are full of the meaner ſort of people, and the chiefe Agents was willfully let gone; after which there was Order taken for by the Committee and Juſtices, having therefore
<pb facs="tcp:112389:4"/>maturely and judiciouſly conſidered, that the chief ſpring of all our miſeries deſcends from thoſe corrupt Fountains, have thought it meete and expedient that there ſhould a troop of horſe daily at the Lord <hi>Paulet</hi> his houſe, for the more ſecurity of the peace of the ſhire, and ſo about e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of the ſaid Gentlemens houſes a Troope of horſe for their apprehending, that therby the Countymay be cleanſed rom ſuch corrupt mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers that contaminate the ſanctity of the Lowes in an obſtinate exulcecration: but it is to be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red they are gone out of the ſhire elſe they would have bin taken ere this, in regard of their dayly ſearches made about their houſes, and in moſt parts of the ſhire.</p>
            <p>On Friday after the muſtering of the trayned Bands, there was a privie ſear<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h at one Miſtris Ward her houſe a widdow woman, and a great Recuſant for M. <hi>Smith</hi> neere <hi>Bridgewater,</hi> and at Mr. <hi>Harvies</hi> houſe an Alderman ſometime of <hi>Baidgewater,</hi> for Sir <hi>Iohn Stowell,</hi> but no perſon found therein, but there was Ammunition and Armour found in widdow <hi>Ward</hi> her houſe, for above 100. ſouldiers.</p>
            <p>A little boy ſeeing the Rifling of the Houſe, ſaid that his Father had a great company of ſuch Ouns too; hereupon the Searchers went with the Child, and fearched all that Village of <hi>Ware,</hi> and took from the widdow <hi>Ward</hi> and neere upon 400. Arms, and many ſorts of Engines, the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants
<pb facs="tcp:112389:5"/>were all committed to ſafe cuſtody: and this is all for the preſent I can certifie you with all, till the next Poſt.</p>
            <p>The Captains of the City of <hi>London</hi> were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to attend the Committee for Defence of the Kingdom, to conſider of fit and convenient places for the making of Out-works for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence and ſafety of the City of <hi>London,</hi> and the Suburbs thereof.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="license">
            <p>Ordered to be forthwith printed.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Brown Cler. Parl.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
